All right בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, so all right, so
today's דף daf is ל"ז, Lamed Zayin, 37, and we are continuing
with the משנה, Mishnah, which is a משנה Mishnah that sort of
says these are the things that are אסור משום שבות. asur mishum
shvut. So it's a very interesting category of שבות, shvut, which we
can sort of apply pretty much universally
to איסורי דרבנן issurei d'rabbanan on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom
Tov. But the משנה Mishnah only mentions a small collection of them
and the question is like exactly what makes them specific and unique.
And we saw that the בבלי Bavli yesterday dealt with a couple
of these about going up on the tree and riding on an
animal and going in the water and clapping and dancing, and all
those are a type of a גזירה gezeira lest you come to
make a musical instrument, lest you come to break off a branch.
And as I pointed out, there's no indication that that's the issue
in the משנה Mishnah and other,
the תוספתא Tosefta and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi do not frame it at
all
as a גזירה. gezeira. And it seems that what's really going on
here in terms of originally what the conceptual concept was in terms
of the משנה, Mishnah, and I'm just repeating what I said yesterday,
was that these are things which we might now call עובדא דחול
uvda d'chol and שבות shvut meaning preserving the nature of שבת. Shabbat.
And these are things that much more are weekday types of activity,
you know, you get in your car and you drive on the
weekday, forgetting the issues of
מלאכה. melacha. Driving around on your horse and on your animal is
the types of things that you do in the
weekday. Clapping and dancing in the original context was doing it out
in the field and you were scaring away the birds, so that
was tending to your crops. Going up in the tree was things
you did when you were cutting down the fruit. So these were
basically activities that were very much weekday activities and therefore אסור משום
שבות, asur mishum shvut, they were very much business type of activities.
But the בבלי, Bavli, as it does very often, frames things in
terms of גזירה gezeira and a safeguard. And I'll just say one
sentence about that, you know, תוספות Tosfos therefore classically discusses what's the
case about the fact that we do clap and dance? Again, not
in the scaring away the birds context, but in like the שול
shul context or whatever it is, in the שמחה simcha context. And
תוספות Tosfos says well, since the whole thing is גזירה gezeira lest
you come to make a musical instrument or fix a musical instrument,
and we nowadays don't trivially fix musical instruments, that גזירה gezeira doesn't
apply and therefore we're allowed to do it. And that's not here,
it's in other places.
Okay, very hard to find here. It's not here, that's why it's
hard to find. Right, exactly. So it's on ל' עמוד א'. Lamed
Amud Aleph.
Fine, it's in multiple places, it's not
here. Anyway, so, you know, for some people that's, oh great, so
every time the reason doesn't apply, the הלכה halakha doesn't apply. Of
course, that goes totally against the general principle which is אף על
פי שבטלה, af al pi shebatla, which was in the beginning of
ביצה Beitzah as
well, אף על פי שבטלה הטעם לא בטלה הגזירה, af al pi
shebatla hata'am lo batla hagezeira, דכל דבר שבמנין צריך מנין אחר להתירו.
d'kol davar she'b'minyan tzarich minyan acher l'hati'ro. So sometimes הלכות halakhot are
intended in a particular context and not when that context doesn't apply,
but normally you need pretty strong evidence to show that that's the
case. So it should be noted that תוספות Tosfos only did this
as when he was doing what תוספות Tosfos usually doing is dealing
with a divergence between the actual practice out in the field, out
in the community, and when that diverged from what the גמרא Gemara
said, תוספות Tosfos rather than saying oh everybody's sinning and we have
to tell them they're all doing the wrong thing and change what
they're doing, תוספות Tosfos finds a way to reconcile it with the
גמרא Gemara to interpret the גמרא Gemara in a way that it's
not a contradiction. And so one of the ways he uses is
the possibility well maybe if the reason isn't any relevant, that can
explain how we deal with the phenomena that people are practicing in
violation, maybe this is one of those cases where when the reason
goes away the גזירה gezeira goes away. But תוספות Tosfos was only
prepared to say that when he had to deal with the facts
on the ground that people were not actually abiding by it. And
as I mentioned before we started, so this becomes a most challenging
issue in another issue that the בבלי Bavli translates in terms of
a גזירה gezeira is not taking medicine on שבת. Shabbos. Again, there's
no evidence in the earlier sources that the problem with taking medicine
was a problem that you'll come to grind the medicine. That's what
the בבלי Bavli says, it makes it a גזירה. gezeira. It might
just be that no, that's just a type of a weekday activity,
you know, particularly if taking medicine usually is not just taking pills
from a bottle but going to a healer and having the healer
you know sort of do some who knows magical stuff or not
magical herbs or whatever, but the whole activity even if it's not
about grinding, again is like going to see a professional on שבת
Shabbat and involving yourself in a professional activity on שבת, Shabbat, you
know, providing medicine and so on. And if you take a look
in the Gospels by the way where you see that Jesus does
healing on שבת, Shabbat, again the sense you get is that it's
and the Pharisees are very upset, the sense you get is that
it's intrinsically that's like the same way riding on an animal like
ugh you don't do that on שבת, Shabbat, it's like a violation.
But nevertheless the בבלי Bavli frames it as a גזירה gezeira you'll
come to grind. And by framing it as a גזירה gezeira gives
the opening and the possibility that when that doesn't apply maybe there's
something to talk about. So for example since we're talking about יום
טוב, Yom Tov, we should mention it. On יום טוב Yom Tov
you're allowed to grind spices. So you can grind on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, so if the whole problem is lest you grind, maybe
categorically
יום טוב Yom Tov was excluded. Anyway, others want to say look
nowadays, given that there's an issue of צער Tza'ar and given that
there's an issue of that we don't grind our own medicine, maybe
this shouldn't apply. Okay, and now it's rare to find a פוסק
Posek that will out and out say it doesn't apply because again,
the basic assumption is even when the reason goes away, like we
learned at the beginning of מסכת, Masechet, the prohibition still remains. But
because there's seen to be this huge divergence between the reason and
the prohibition, it leads to פוסקים Poskim to be more creative in
interpreting what exactly are the parameters. Like what type of like some
will be very liberal, like for example, if you're חולה כל הגוף,
Chole kol haguf, you're allowed to take medicine. You're only not allowed
to take medicine if it's called a מיחוש בעלמא, Michush b'alma, a
little discomfort, because they didn't restrict it for somebody that was חולה
כל הגוף. Chole kol haguf. So then like a lot of פוסקים
Poskim nowadays will be very liberal in defining people as חולה כל
הגוף Chole kol haguf in order to allow them to take medicine.
Once there's this divergence between the reason and the and the prohibition.
But again, the interesting fact is, and with this we'll move on,
number one, another example, not on our דף, Daf, but another example
of how the בבלי Bavli frames all these things as גזירה שמא,
Gezeirah shema, not as an intrinsic issue. And then number two, how
that leads to
possibilities when those reasons don't apply, that even though there's generally this
resistance to saying that things change based on changing reasons, as we
saw every now and then תוספות Tosafot does it when the practice
is in divergence, and it sometimes also can lead פוסקים Poskim to
thinking a little bit more creatively in terms of how to define
the parameters once it's being framed in terms of a גזירה. Gezeirah.
Yes.
And he would go the other way, seeing as well, it's really
intrinsically a problem, not so much the medicine then going to the
doctor, then you shouldn't go to the doctor if you're not feeling
too well, you know what I mean? Like you know?
Yeah, well that's the thing. I mean in a way by framing
it as a גזירה Gezeirah it gives more latitude. So as opposed
an intrinsic problem gives a lot less. Yes.
Doesn't מתקן כלי Metaken kli
mean fix the instrument or tune it and make it appropriate for
you?
That's a good question. I mean מתקן, Metaken, you know, would there
be considered to be like at least some דרבנן D'rabbanan problem of
tuning? You know, we I don't know if there's any direct evidence
of that. I mean if it's really considered to be, it gets
to a larger question, you know, when is something considered broken and
at what stage it's a natural thing to have to retune? It'd
hard to be imagine that that would ever be that that would
be considered a biblical thing. If it's, you know, if it's significantly
out of tune, like the whole issue of the knife, at what
stage does the knife stop being a כלי, Kli, a knife? It's
a good question. Let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, three
lines from the bottom on ל"ו עמוד ב'. Lamed vav amud bet.
ואלו הן משום רשות. V'eilu hein mishum reshut. And the following things
are for רשות, Reshut, meaning that they're still prohibited as a שבות,
Shvut, but it's a type of activity that is not completely neutral.
It's a type of activity that there is now רשות Reshut often
means completely discretionary, but it's contrasted to מצוה Mitzvah and actually here
what it means is things that there actually is some מצוה Mitzvah
component to. Maybe it's not an out and out מצוה Mitzvah but
there is some מצוה Mitzvah component to it and nevertheless remains forbidden.
So what are they? So לא דנין. Lo danin. The first one
is you can't sit in a בית דין. Beit din. So again,
והא מצוה קא עביד, V'ha mitzvah ka avid, what do you mean?
Being sitting in a בית דין Beit din is a מצוה. Mitzvah.
Right? I mean, you know, there's all these פסוקים Psukim about how
you're supposed to judge ושפטו, V'shafatu, you know, בין איש ובין אחיו
ובין... Bein ish u'vein achiv u'vein... what is it? ובין גרו. U'vein
geiro. ובין גרו, U'vein geiro, right. Anyway. Okay, והא מצוה קא עביד?
V'ha mitzvah ka avid? So גמרא Gemara says לא צריכא דאיכא דעדיף
מיניה. Lo tzricha d'ika d'adif minei. No, because actually there's somebody always
better to sit in דין. Din. So therefore, which is an important
like thing. Like oh, I'm going to I'm going to be the
דיין Dayan here. You know, don't think you're doing such a מצוה,
Mitzvah, there's other there are better people to be doing this than
you. So therefore it's not an out and out מצוה. Mitzvah. There's
a מצוה Mitzvah element because you know, yet that's why like משה
Moshe had the whole system. You don't always go to the best
judge, you know, there's other levels of judges as well. But in
many cases it's not an out and out מצוה Mitzvah because there
could always be going to somebody better. Okay, ולא מקדשין, V'lo mikadshin,
and you can't do קידושין. Kiddushin. So גמרא Gemara says והא מצוה
קא עביד? V'ha mitzvah ka avid? Why isn't that called why is
that called a רשות? Reshut? Call it a מצוה. Mitzvah. So גמרא
Gemara says לא צריכא, Lo tzricha, you need it for a case
דאית ליה אשה ובנים, D'it lei isha u'banim, that he already is
married and has kids and he's done the מצוה Mitzvah פרו ורבו.
P'ru u'rvu. Now this is quite fascinating because this makes it sound
that the entire מצוה Mitzvah of getting married is for the aspects
of having children. And you know, it's actually quite an interesting מחלוקת
ראשונים Machloket Rishonim whether there's a מצוה Mitzvah to get married at
all.
Some ראשונים Rishonim say that there is, and a מצוה Mitzvah to
get married, but it's basically framed as, it sounds like this in
the רמב"ם Rambam and the מאירי Meiri and other ראשונים, Rishonim, that
it's a מצוה Mitzvah to get married but it's because it enables
the מצוה Mitzvah of פרו ורבו. P'ru u'rvu. It's like a הכשר
מצוה Hechsher mitzvah for פרו ורבו, P'ru u'rvu, which is what this
גמרא Gemara sounds like. Others like the ראש Rosh say it isn't
even a מצוה Mitzvah to get married because you could in theory
a person could be מקיים Mekayem פרו ורבו P'ru u'rvu out of
wedlock. Even if you have kids out of wedlock, you're still מקיים
Mekayem פרו ורבו. P'ru u'rvu. So he says that it's not even
a מצוה Mitzvah at all. Okay, now it might not practically you
know, in theory you might not need to get married in order
to have kids but hopefully people are having their kids in marriage
and practically it's certainly the first step to having and raising kids.
So but the גמרא Gemara says that but but if you've already
been יוצא Yotzei פרו ורבו, P'ru u'rvu, there's no... Not a particular
מצוה. mitzvah. Now again, that's a little bit disturbing that the only
aspect of the value of the, the, you know, the מצוה mitzvah
of getting married is the idea of having kids. There are גמרות
Gemaras and I guess we'll get to them when we get to
נשים Nashim that talk about an intrinsic value of marriage beyond having
kids. I mean how about the פסוקים psukim לא טוב היות האדם
לבדו? lo tov heyot ha'adam levado? You know, כל אדם ששרוי בלא
אשה, kol adam she-sharui belo ishah, again all from the male perspective,
שרוי בלא טובה, sharui belo tovah, בלא שמחה, belo simchah, בלא, belo,
you know, בלא כפרה, belo kaparah, you know, it speaks about the
intrinsic value of being married. But what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is that right now technically it's not a מצוה. mitzvah. And that's
also important, right? Like is a person obligated, a person has had
kids, his wife gets divorced, his wife dies, does he have to
feel like, again from the male perspective I'm talking now, oh, now
I have to get married, there's a מצוה mitzvah to get married
so I can't stay single? You know, so it's, you know, so
saying it's not a מצוה mitzvah on the one hand seems to
devalue it, but on the other hand also says that it's not
a strict obligation beyond the strict obligation to have kids. Okay, so
and there are other גמרות Gemaras that speak about its value. So
here the גמרא Gemara does say we, it's in a context where
there's not a מצוה mitzvah element because you were already יוצא yotze
פרו ורבו. pru urvu. By the way, תוספות Tosafot raises, תוספות Tosafot
from the Mainz... By the way, תוספות Tosafot raises the question, the
assumption here when the גמרא Gemara says isn't it a מצוה, mitzvah,
isn't it a מצוה mitzvah is just a categorical, is just a
question of how it was labeled. Why is it labeled in the
רשות reshut column, why not label it in the מצוה mitzvah column?
But תוספות Tosafot suggests another read. And תוספות Tosafot suggests if this
were actually a מצוה, mitzvah, it should be allowed on שבת Shabbos
and יום טוב. Yom Tov. And תוספות Tosafot raises the possibility that
somebody who has not yet, a man who has not yet had
kids, could actually get married on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom
Tov. When it becomes a מצוה, mitzvah, it actually will become allowed.
And that's the גמרא's Gemara question, it should be a מצוה mitzvah
and it should be allowed. Now again, that's very much not פשט,
pshat, because the next category in the משנה Mishnah are things that
are מצוות mitzvahs and are also forbidden. So, it's a hard read
of this גמרא, Gemara, but it is interesting that תוספות Tosafot raises
that possibility. Yes?
A question: do the ראשונים Rishonim also raise utilitarian reasons for getting
married for stability of society?
Yeah, I mean, so a lot of those reasons we'll see, there's
again a famous סוגיא sugya about that in יבמות Yevamot that talk
about reasons and those reasons come up. So, yeah.
Because if you put something in the מצוה mitzvah category such that
it automatically becomes מותר, mutar, it could be a good read because
then all you have to do is list the exceptions to that,
right?
Yeah, but then the משנה Mishnah should have been more explicit, like,
you know, and again, the second, the last part of the משנה
Mishnah is the following things are מצוות mitzvahs and are also forbidden
משום שבות. mishum shvut. So yeah, but it is fascinating, תוספות Tosafot
in general often quotes רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam as trying to give
greater allowance to get married when the גמרא Gemara thinks you're not,
like about even getting married when the woman is in אבילות avelus
because, you know, because, you know, because, or I forget, I forget
the exact case, but whether the woman was in אבילות avelus or
the man was in אבילות. avelus. שמא יקדמנו אחר.
shema yikadmenu acher.
Well, not שמא יקדמנו אחר, shema yikadmenu acher, because again, the need
to take care of the kids, and the need to have kids,
and whatever, so it's actually interesting, it probably speaks to the reality,
I'm trying to remember the exact תוספות, Tosafot, anyway, it probably speaks
to the realities of, you know, of often people succumbing to, you
know, death and violence in the Middle Ages, and the importance of
making sure that everybody gets married when they need to be getting
married. Yeah?
What I was gonna say before was that I don't know if
the גמרא's Gemara conferring anything from here about not being a מצוה
mitzvah for the woman to get married, because it didn't say like,
let's say if she was never married.
No, no, no, the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו pru urvu is
on the man, at least that's the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara
in יבמות. Yevamot. Okay, let's take a look.
Wait, sorry, I thought we were
here too, what the גמרא's Gemara assumption here, what, if it's even
less of a מצוה mitzvah
when you already have kids. Right, so I mean that implies A,
that it's a מצוה mitzvah in general, and B, that it's still
a מצוה. mitzvah.
Right, דוב Dov makes a good point, which is that רשות reshut
doesn't mean there's no מצוה mitzvah at all, it means that it's
not as much of a מצוה. mitzvah. Right, thank you, that's important.
Right, right, so right there still is an element, right, thank you,
so right, it's like second line from רש"י, Rashi, ומיהא קצת מצוה
איכא, umiha k'tzat mitzvah ika, as it says, but of course for
רש"י, Rashi, קצת מצוה k'tzat mitzvah is the value of having more
than the minimum kids, בבוקר זרע את זרעך ולערב אל תנח ידך.
be-voker zera et zar'acha vela-erev al tanach yadecha. So רש"י Rashi still
sees the קצת מצוה k'tzat mitzvah in terms of the kids, except
having more than the minimum. But you are absolutely correct that the
idea here of רשות reshus. does not mean non, you know, not
at all a מצוה, mitzvah, it just means that it's a, not
as much of a מצוה mitzvah as other things. Okay, so now
let's continue: לא חולצין ולא מייבמין, lo choltzin vela meyabmin, you don't
do חליצה chalitzah and יבום. yibum. במצוה קא עביד! be-mitzvah ka avid!
What do you mean, it's a מצוה mitzvah to do יבום yibum
or חליצה? chalitzah? I mean, question which one comes first. But the
גמרא Gemara says no, לא צריכא דאיכא גדול, lo tzricha de-ika gadol,
sort of like the answer before by the בית דין. beis din.
There's an older brother, okay, ומצוה בגדול לייבם, u-mitzvah be-gadol leyabem, and
the older one is supposed to be the one who does the
יבום, yibum, the first responsibility goes to him. So again, as we're
saying, it doesn't mean there's no מצוה mitzvah for you, but it's
not as much of an out and out מצוה.
mitzvah. If there's an older brother...
alright, fine, yeah, but then you'd be in the next category which
is the מצוה mitzvah category. וכולהו טעמא מאי? ve-khulhu ta'ama mai? Now
here again gets the key line. And why can't you do these
things? קידושין, kiddushin, יבום, yibum, חליצה, chalitzah, דין, din, גזירה שמא יכתוב?
gezeirah shema yichtov? Because you'll write things down. You have a court
case, you have to keep notes. You're getting married, you want to
write the
specifics. and you want to write the deals and the financial arrangements.
You're doing יבום *Yibum* and חליצה *Chalitzah* also, you want to make
a record of it. So again, not because this thing is intrinsically
transactional or status changed, again, not because there's an intrinsic sense that
these are things that don't happen on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* and יום
טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, again being framed as a גזירה gezeira.
*gezeirah*.
Okay, I know.
So that's my point. Why didn't it just say intrinsically it's a
type of a transactional type of a thing or, even though it's
interpersonal and it's status or whatever, and that itself makes it inappropriate?
ואידך שבות shvus, *V'idach shvus*. But again, it's the בבלי Bavli *Bavli*'s
insistence on framing this as a גזירה gezeira *gezeirah*. Okay, we'll see
that now. The possibility of an intrinsic problem is going to come
up in a minute. ואלו הן משום מצוה mitzvah לא lo, מקדישין
ולא מעריכין ולא מחרימין *V'eilu hein mishum mitzvah lo makdishin v'lo maarichin
v'lo machrimin*. Okay, so you don't sanctify things and מעריכין *maarichin* and
מחרימין *machrimin*, other ways of sanctifying things. גזירה gezeira משום מקח וממכר
mishum mekach u'memkar, *Gezeirah mishum mekach u'memkar*. Lest it lead to business.
Now why? Because this is again very transactional and changing possession of
the objects. Now as opposed to like those said before, what about
like making a pledge in שול *shul* isn't changing possession of the
object, but actually giving something over to הקדש *hekdesh* is. Now why
is מקח וממכר mekach u'memkar, *mekach u'memkar* a problem? So if you
look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י *Rashi* gives two reasons and this
exactly plays out on the tension we've been talking about, or the
two possibilities we've been talking about. So רש"י *Rashi* four lines down
in the narrow lines, משום מקח וממכר mishum mekach u'memkar, *mishum mekach
u'memkar* says, דלמקח וממכר דמו שמוציא מרשות לרשות הקדש *d'limkach u'memkar damu
shemotzi meirashus lirashus hekdesh*. You take it out of your possession into
the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*'s possession. ומקח וממכר אסור assur. מן המקרא
דכתיב ממצוא חפצך ודבר דבר *U'mekach u'memkar assur min hamikra de'ksiv mimtzo
cheftzecha v'daber davar*. Because he says you're not supposed to pursue your
pursuits on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. So meaning it's business activity, so it's
intrinsically problematic. You don't have to make it a גזירה gezeira *gezeirah*,
it's intrinsically problematic. אי נמי *Ei nami*, says רש"י *Rashi*, מקח וממכר
mekach u'memkar אתי לידי כתיבה שאר מכירה *mekach u'memkar asi lidei ksivah
shear mechira*. Or it's a גזירה *gezeirah*, you'll come to write things
down. והשתא הוי גזירה לגזירה *V'hashta havei gezeirah l'gezeirah*. So if מקח
וממכר mekach u'memkar. *mekach u'memkar* is itself a גזירה *gezeirah*, so this
is a גזירה לגזירה *gezeirah l'gezeirah*? No, כולא חד גזירה היא *kula
chad gezeirah hi*. It's all part of מקח וממכר *mekach u'memkar*. So
again, this is saying exactly this question. Is this thing intrinsically problematic?
It's business-like, and therefore intrinsically you don't do it on שבת Shabbos.
*Shabbos*? Or is the whole thing just a safeguard to writing things
down and to doing a מלאכה *melacha*?
Yeah. Well, why don't they use the language of קנין *kinyan*? Or
is this the reasons why you don't make a קנין *kinyan* on
שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* also? You'd come and write it down, you'd come...
Right, so basically...
But because קנינים *kinyanim* you can do under certain circumstances. Business is
much more absolutely forbidden. Like you can give gifts on יום טוב
Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* in particular, you can give gifts on שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos* if you're going to do it לצורך שבת Shabbos *l'tzorech
Shabbos*. מקח וממכר *Mekach u'memkar* is not just possession in itself. Right,
but קנין *kinyan* is under certain... under other circumstances, קנין *kinyan* is
part of the מקח וממכר *mekach u'memkar*, yeah.
It really seems to me then if you're doing an appeal, it
completely seems to be a problem משום
שמא יכתוב *mishum shema yichtov*. Yeah, so but part of the reason
is also ממצוא חפצך ודבר דבר *mimtzo cheftzecha v'daber davar*, then it
has that intrinsic problem, but then it has the exemption of חפצי
שמים *cheftzei shamayim*, right? So then you can't... but then you could
say קידושין *Kiddushin* and יבום *Yibum* is also חפצי שמים *cheftzei shamayim*
in a certain sense. So but yeah, but part of that is
also because you know, what makes it business-like as opposed to no,
this is actually very religious activity. It's חפצי שמים *cheftzei shamayim*.
And you can still be worried... you could still be religiously oriented
but still have another reason which is שמא יכתוב *shema yichtov*, right?
You'll want to write down how much this guy owes...
Right, right. True, it's true. We frame that but that's not actual...
that hasn't actual change possession. That's just a pledge. Okay, anyway, but
you're right. I mean, concerns of שמא יכתוב *shema yichtov* are pretty
reasonable in that circumstance. And שול *shul*'s come up with creative ways
of handling it with little paper clips or what. Let's keep on
going. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: ולא מגביהין
תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'ma'asros. *v'lo magbihin trumos u'maasros*. So you don't take
תרומות ומעשרות Trumos U'maasros, *trumos u'maasros*. Again, that's a מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*
but it's not allowed. פשיטא *Pshita*. Obvious. Not so obvious, but okay,
obvious. Because again, maybe there's some sense of fixing something. And that's
an איסור *issur* like we saw before about taking things to the
מקוה *mikvah*. You're changing status, you're fixing it, it's like making something
on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* and יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. By
the way, that's a final פשיטא *pshita* presumably because it's intrinsically a
problem, not a גזירה *gezeirah*, right? So that the very same פשיטא
*pshita* means it's like itself obvious that itself evident that that's going
to be a problem presumably again not because of גזירה *gezeirah*. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this: תני רב Rav, יוסף
לא lo, נצרכה אלא ela, ליתנה לכהן בו ביום *Tani Rav Yosef
lo nitzrecha ela litnah l'kohen bo bayom*. Now the חידוש *chiddush* is
you can't even separate the תרומות ומעשרות *trumos u'maasros* and give it
to the כהן kohein. *kohen*. If you're giving it to the כהן
kohein *kohen*, then it's not so much like you're coming to fix
your food and you're doing something which is fixing and changing on
שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*. You're coming to give a gift to the כהן
kohein, *kohen* and we know you can give gifts of food to
people on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, even on שבת Shabbos
*Shabbos*, but certainly on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* we've been
discussing it. So maybe that reframes what's happening. Okay, so that's why
even so it remains forbidden. והני מילי v'hanei mili, פירא דטביל מאתמול
*V'hani mili pira d'tavil me'etmol*. Now this thing that it's forbidden is
only fruit (this is now we're talking on יום טוב Yom Tov
*Yom Tov*) that was טבל *tevel* the day before. אבל פירא דטביל
האידנא *Aval pira d'tavil ha'idna*, things that become טבל *tevel* today. What
can become טבל *tevel* today? I mean, that comes
through processing it, which it should have happened... can't happen on יום
טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. No, there's one thing that can become
טבל *tevel* on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. כגון עיסה להפריש
ממנה חלה challah, *k'gon issa l'hafrish mimena challah*. On יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov* you can make fresh bread. Not on שבת Shabbos
*Shabbos*, but on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. So you've made
your fresh bread on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* and you've
made your... dough and now you have to take חלה. challah, That
מפרישין ומבילין לכהן. mafrishin u'mavilin l'kohein. That you can take it and
give it to the כהן. kohein Now, two things: one, why? Number
one is it falls under the אוכל נפש ochel nefesh היתר, heter,
if you can actually make the חלה, challah, we're going to allow
you to be מפריש, mafrish, you make the bread, we're going to
allow you to be מפריש mafrish חלה, challah because that's again the
היתר heter the אוכל נפש ochel nefesh allowance. And but what's interesting
to also note is the גמרא Gemara seems to point out ומבילין
לכהן. u'mavilin l'kohein. Don't just be מפריש mafrish the חלה, challah. it
seems to be the point of the גמרא, Gemara don't just be
מפריש mafrish חלה challah and put it aside. Give it to the
כהן kohein because that makes it look also a little bit more
כשר. kosher. That makes it look like it's about giving it to
the כהן, not about fixing the חלה. That seems to be what
the גמרא Gemara is saying although להלכה, l'halacha,
the פוסקים poskim do not underscore the need to give it to
the כהן because now you have the reality nowadays by חלת חוץ
לארץ. challas chutz l'aretz. חלת חוץ לארץ challas chutz l'aretz isn't given
to the כהן and nevertheless you can be מפריש mafrish חלה on
יום טוב Yom Tov for dough that you made on יום טוב.
Yom Tov, Okay, but here it does say ומבילין לכהן u'mavilin l'kohein
which the גמרא Gemara said before makes it better. Okay, והני v'hanei
מילי, okay, והני now now the גמרא Gemara goes back to the
whole list. והני משום רשות איכא משום שבות ליכא. v'hanei mishum reshus
ika mishum shvus leka. The גמרא Gemara says I don't understand why
it called that middle category רשות. reshus רשות reshus? means to sound
like it's not problematic. It's a completely, you know, optional or quasi
מצוה mitzvah thing. But the whole point is is that there are
שבת Shabbos prohibitions around it. And how about the last category? והני
משום מצוה איכא משום שבות ליכא? v'hanei mishum mitzvah ika mishum shvus
leka? What do you mean calling them מצוה, mitzvah not calling them
רשות? reshus The whole reason they are a problem is because they're
also a שבות, shvus. they're also some of these rabbinic restrictions. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי יצחק לאו מיבעיא קאמר. amar Rabi
Yitzchak lav mibaya ka'amar. No, no, no, you have to read the
משנה. Mishnah. Everything is a שבות. shvus But לאו מיבעיא שבות גרידתא,
lav mibaya shvus gerideta, it goes without saying you can't do things
which are just a שבות shvus. only problematic and have no redeeming
qualities דאסור d'assur that that clearly is forbidden. אלא אפילו שבות דרשות,
ela afilu shvus d'reshus, when it calls this category רשות reshus doesn't
mean it's not a שבות. shvus. Everything is a שבות. shvus But
even things that are a שבות shvus that are also have a
רשות component, which means also have some type of a quasi מצוה
mitzvah, component, נמי אסור, nami assur, even those are forbidden. דלאו מיבעיא
שבות דרשות דאסור, d'lav mibaya shvus d'reshus d'assur, not only things with
a quasi מצוה component, אלא אפילו שבות דמצוה נמי אסור, ela afilu
shvus d'mitzvah nami assur, even things that are a שבות shvus, that
have an added מצוה, even that is אסור. assur And that clearly
is the פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so we went
through the whole list, explained what the reasons are. Mostly we've explained
that they were גזירות. gezeiros. One or two might not be גזירות.
gezeiros. מקח וממכר, although מקח וממכר wasn't listed, it said משום מקח
וממכר, so that should be noted. That when the גמרא Gemara says
you don't get, you know, you don't sanctify or whatever, משום מקח
וממכר, it still made it a גזירה. A גזירה to something which
might be intrinsically אסור assur מקח וממכר. Okay, so even there it
was still working in the גזירה category. The one case where maybe
it wasn't working in the גזירה category was the separating of תרומות
ומעשרות. Okay, the last line says all of these are אסור assur
on יום טוב Yom Tov. קל וחומר kal v'chomer בשבת. b'Shabbos. There's
no difference between יום טוב Yom Tov and שבת Shabbos אלא אוכל
נפש. ela ochel nefesh. כל אלו ביום טוב אמרו. kol elu b'Yom
Tov amru. All these were said by יום
טוב. Yom Tov ורמינהו, u'raminhu, the גמרא Gemara asks you, we have
our previous משנה, Mishnah, משילין דרך ארובה ביום טוב אבל לא בשבת.
mashilin derech arubah b'Yom Tov aval lo b'Shabbos. You can lower the
fruit down the skylight on יום טוב Yom Tov? and not on
שבת. Shabbos So look, there is a difference that's not related to
אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, a difference on a דרבנן. d'rabanan. Okay, so
there are differences at דרבנן d'rabanan levels between יום טוב Yom Tov
and שבת. Shabbat, I mean we've seen a lot of differences. Okay,
but this difference is maybe not immediately in the context of food
preparation, although it is about saving food from—but again that's more about
הפסד. hefsed. רש״י Rashi underscored it in yesterday's דף daf that you're
not going to eat the food today. So it's not about eating
food and nevertheless we were more lenient, it said explicitly in the
משנה Mishnah that this allowance is going to be a יום טוב
Yom Tov allowance, not a שבת allowance. So you see there are
differences that aren't limited to אוכל נפש. ochel nefesh. So אמר רב
יוסף לא קשיא. amar Rav Yosef lo kashya. It's not difficult. הא
רבי אליעזר הא רבי יהושע. ha Rabi Eliezer ha Rabi Yehoshua. There's
a debate between רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua
whether you give people more latitude on יום טוב Yom Tov in
order to save things from for הפסד hefsed reasons. דתניא d'tanya we
learn a ברייתא. braisa. אותו ואת בנו שנפלו לבור. oso v'es bno
she'naflu l'bor. You have a mother and a baby calf that fell
into a well. Okay, and you can't have both of them today
because there's a prohibition to slaughter the אותו ואת בנו. oso v'es
bno. So but you want to bring them both out of the
well but you can't claim that it's both for food purposes because
there's no way you can eat both. Not only you, no way
anybody can eat, can eat, you know, no way you can even
divide it between another person. So what do you do? So רבי
אליעזר אומר מעלה את הראשון על מנת לשוחטו ושוחטו. Rabi Eliezer omer
ma'aleh es harishon al menas l'shochto v'shochto. You bring up the first
one and say I'm going to שחט shacht the mother cow and
you bring up the mother
cow and then you have to שחט shacht it. והשני v'hasheini cause,
you know, you could only bring up the one you're going to
eat.
והשני עושה לו פרנסה במקומו v'hasheini oseh lo parnasa b'mkomo and the
second one you have to lower down food where it is but
you're not allowed to bring it out of the well. That would
be too much טרחא tircha whatever on יום טוב Yom Tov כדי
שלא ימות k'dei shelo yamis so that you can try to do
what you need to so it doesn't die. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabi
Yehoshua omer, רבי יהושע Rabi Yehoshua says no, I got a better
solution. מעלה את הראשון על מנת לשוחטו ואינו שוחטו. ma'aleh es harishon
al menas l'shochto v'eino shochto. You bring up the first one, you
say you're going to שחט shacht and then after it gets out
of the well you say you know what, I changed my mind.
This one looks a little scrawny, I think I'm going to eat
the second one. וחוזר ומרים ומעלה השני v'chozer u'mirim u'ma'aleh hasheini and
then you bring out the second one to eat. And now you're
not even restricted to eat the second one. You could change your
mind again. רצה זה שוחט רצה זה. ratza zeh shochet ratza zeh.
רצה זה שוחט רצה זה שוחט. Ratza zeh shochet ratza zeh shochet.
You can שחט shecht whichever one you want. So you do a
little trick that allows you to take both out of the well.
So what the גמרא Gemara says is רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is
who gives you more latitude to do things to prevent them from
getting destroyed, also it's a case of animals and there's a צער
בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim issue but presumably also to allow to
prevent things from getting destroyed. He was the one in the previous
משנה Mishna that let you lower the fruit down the skylight. Our
משנה Mishna that says there are no differences and don't have extra
allowances for saving things from being destroyed, that would be רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer who had no extra allowances. So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back, ממאי?
mi-mai? Who says it's the same issue? דילמא עד כאן לא קאמר
רבי אליעזר התם אלא דאפשר בפרנסה. Dilma ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi
Eliezer hatam ela de'efshar bapar'nasa. Maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was strict
there because he figured, look, you can save the animal even without
taking it out of the well. You can lower down food. אבל
הכא, Aval hacha, by the fruit that's rotting on the roof, it's
about to rain or whatever the case is, דלא אפשר בפרנסה, delo
efshar bapar'nasa, that there's no way to protect it unless you actually
lower it down the skylight, לא, lo, he would not restrict it.
Maybe he'd let you do the case of the fruit on the
roof. אינמי, Inami, or say the opposite. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי
יהושע התם אלא דאפשר לארומי. Ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehoshua hatam
ela de'efshar la'arumey. Why does רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua let you bring
them both out of the well? Because you can trick, you can
make it look as though each one you're doing for the sake
of eating. אבל הכא דלא אפשר לארומי, Aval hacha delo efshar la'arumey,
here there's no way you can trick, it's clear that you're not
going to be eating a thousand pounds of dried out grapes or
whatever it is, of drying raisins, of drying raisins, לא, lo, maybe
he wouldn't allow you. So there's no clear linking of this debate
to the previous משנה Mishna and saying the previous משנה Mishna is
not דברי הכל. divrei hakol. And we still have something that's allowed
on יום טוב Yom Tov, that's not allowed on שבת that's not
related directly to eating food. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא, okay.
אלא אמר רב פפא לא קשיא. Ela amar Rav Papa lo kashya.
Here, you're right, it is, again it's debated, and these two משניות
Mishnayot are going like different opinions. הא בית שמאי הא בית הלל,
Ha Beit Shammai ha Beit Hillel, and it's a בית שמאי Beit
Shammai בית הלל Beit Hillel debate. דתנן, De-nan, we taught in a
משנה: Mishna: בית שמאי אומרים אין מוציאין לא את הקטן ולא את
הלולב ולא את ספר תורה לרשות הרבים ובית הלל מתירין. Beit Shammai
omrim ein motzi'in lo et hakatan v'lo et halulav v'lo et sefer
Torah lirshut harabim uBeit Hillel matirin. בית שמאי Beit Shammai remember has
all these restrictions on carrying and בית הלל Beit Hillel does not.
Now what does this have to do with the משנה Mishna about
lowering fruit? So the גמרא Gemara is about to ask. But I
want to stop for a minute and say and ask tell you
תוספות's Tosafot question. תוספות Tosafot says what do you mean there's no
difference between שבת and יום טוב Yom Tov. except for food-related issues?
How about carrying? Right, you're allowed to carry on יום טוב, Yom
Tov you're not allowed to carry on שבת. So one answer could
be, yeah, but carrying derives from an allowance about food-related issues, right,
because carrying is seen as connected to food and whatever, מתוך mitoch
and however the explanation goes. תוספות Tosafot says another answer, which is
maybe a variation of the same. Clearly at the biblical level, it's
shocking, at the biblical level there are more differences than just food.
There's also carrying, there's also making fires. But the point is here
the context of this משנה Mishna is rabbinic. So we're focusing on
the issue of the implication that there are no rabbinic differences between
שבת and יום טוב. Yom Tov Biblical maybe there are more than
things that are food and even related to food like carrying and
fire. But the question is no rabbinic differences, and in a previous
משנה Mishna we saw a rabbinic difference. So then the question becomes
how does this relate to בית שמאי Beit Shammai about carrying? What
does that have to do with about dumping your food down the
skylight? So the גמרא Gemara says דילמא לא היא, Dilma lo hi,
so maybe it's not related. עד כאן לא קאמרי בית שמאי התם
אלא הוצאה. Ad kan lo ka'amri Beit Shammai hatam ela hotza'ah. They're
talking about carrying, carrying they put restrictions on. אבל טלטול, Aval tiltul,
moving things around like moving the fruit and dumping it down the
skylight, you know, could all be a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, your
rooftop, so why would they have restrictions? How do you know they'd
be more restrictive? לא, maybe they would not be more restrictive. גמרא
Gemara says לא, אטו טלטול לאו צורך הוצאה הוא? atu tiltul lav
tsorech hotza'ah hu? גמרא Gemara says no, because moving things is really
the first step in carrying them. There's your slippery slope. Now what
does that mean? So many ראשונים Rishonim understand that this phrase טלטול
tiltul is referring to מוקצה muktza and understand that what it's saying
is that one of the reasons that you're not allowed to move
מוקצה muktza is because if you randomly move objects around without any
sense of restriction, then it leads to you not thinking and taking
objects out of your house and things to you leads to carrying.
So that one of the main problems of מוקצה muktza is that
you learn a certain guardedness related to the movement of objects which
leads to, you know, help make sure you don't accidentally carry. And
therefore בית שמאי Beit Shammai who has more problems of carrying on
יום טוב Yom Tov would have more problems of מוקצה muktza and
בית הלל Beit Hillel would have less problems of מוקצה. muktza. Fine,
but until now we've been assuming that the case in our משנה
Mishna about the stuff on the roof wasn't מוקצה. muktza. Remember yesterday's
דף, daf, the whole assumption was covering it because it's not מוקצה
muktza and the whole question is if it is מוקצה muktza can
you cover it? But the whole assumption was that the whole משנה
Mishna was dealing with that it wasn't מוקצה. muktza. So that's very
difficult and what you and רש"י constantly said the problem was just
טרחא. tircha. So then what you have to say is that even
in a non-מוקצה non-muktza area, which makes a certain sense, בית שמאי
Beit Shammai if they're concerned about carrying doesn't want you to do
too much schlepping. טלטול tiltul just means schlepping. Too much schlepping leads
to carrying, even if it's not מוקצה. muktza. So therefore it's reasonable
to say that the previous משנה... Mishna... The previous משנה Mishna was
a בית הלל Beis Hillel which is not so restrictive when it
comes to מוקצה Muktzah and not so restrictive when it comes to
שלעפינג. shlepping. And this משנה Mishna that says there are no differences,
so even in terms of putting the fruit down the skylight, that
would be בית שמאי Beis Shammai who was more restrictive in terms
of areas of מוקצה Muktzah and שלעפינג shlepping and would not let
you dump the fruit down the skylight. Now I have to tell
you it is very bizarre because it makes it sound like the
only difference that you can find between שבת and יום טוב Yom
Tov, outside of cooking issues, the only דרבנן d'rabbanan difference is this
one case
here about dumping the fruit down the skylight. Yesterday's דף daf was
almost like a complete contradiction of this. You remember yesterday's דף daf
when it asked what about this issue about שבת four and five
קופות kupos as opposed to יום טוב? Yom Tov Well maybe יום
טוב Yom Tov will be more מחמיר machmir because אתי לזלזולי בה,
asi lezulzulei beh, or maybe יום טוב Yom Tov will be more
lenient because יום טוב Yom Tov is more קל, kal, etc. It
set up an entire system in which we acknowledge that there would
be different restrictions on שבת and יום טוב Yom Tov, even in
דרבנן d'rabbanan areas, even not related to אוכל נפש. ochel nefesh. So
I really don't know how the גמרא Gemara here has solved the
problem. It only addressed its attention to one משנה. Mishna. There seems
to be a lot more you could be looking at. Anyway so
that is the issue here about שבות, shvus a very important central
category of שבות and the way the בבלי consistently, maybe with the
one exception of תרומות ומעשרות, frames it around גזרה gezeirah issues.
You don't have to connect טלטול tiltul and שלעפינג shlepping to the
first step in הוצאה. hotzaah. It could be מחזי עובדין
דחול.
mechazei
uvdin d'chol.
That's not what the גמרא Gemara. says. The גמרא Gemara. wants to
make it tied to בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי. Beis
Shammai.
Yes, it's interesting.
I know, yesterday we didn't mention הוצאה hotzaah at all.
Next משנה. Mishna. Now we get to a new concept which is
going to be a dominant concept until the end of the מסכת.
masechet. הבהמה והכלים כרגלי הבעלים. Ha-behemah ve-ha-keilim k'raglei ha-baalim. Now this is
an issue of תחומין. techumim. You have a תחום. tchum. You can
only go 2000 אמות amos from your city, from the edges of
your city in all directions unless you make an עירוב. eiruv. And
if you make your עירוב, eiruv, an עירוב תחומין, eiruv techumim, then
it adds, it can add, you put something that designates where you're
starting שבת outside your city or יום טוב, Yom Tov and then
it gives you more distance in one direction and takes it away
from the other. This משנה Mishna introduces the idea that it's not
just where you can go but where your objects can go. And
the relevance is what do I care where my objects can go
if they're not going with me? Well let's say somebody else wants
to use them on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Can you lend somebody
your dishes if that person is going to take them to a
place which is in his תחום tchum but outside of your תחום?
tchum? And the answer is no. They are restricted with this, they
are limited to the same תחום tchum as yours. הבהמה והכלים כרגלי
הבעלים. Ha-behemah ve-ha-keilim k'raglei ha-baalim. It goes like the legs of the
owner. By the way, this does raise a fascinating question which I
will just put to you without answering it because I would have
to look it up, I don't know the answer off the top
of my head, which is let's say you're out of town. I'm
going to be in, I'm going to Hawaii for
פסח. Pesach. And you say, can I go ahead and
use your house, I put some guests in your house, can I
go ahead and use your blankets and whatever? Sure, go ahead, no
problem. Well I don't get it. It's outside of my תחום. tchum.
I'm in Hawaii. So does that mean that you can't move anything
from my house because it's already outside of my תחום? tchum? So
it's an interesting question because the house there is basically... yes.
So it's not conceptually sounds like it's related to the famous מחלוקת
machlokes of שביתת כלים. shvisas keilim.
Well,
yes,
maybe it's a subset of that.
That's interesting, interesting. Is it שביתת כלים shvisas keilim looking about what?
Yeah, it's an interesting question. Let's see what it's based on. But
anyway the way I'm raising it is in a context where fundamentally
the כלים keilim are already disassociated from you. As opposed to fundamentally
I start with my כלים keilim and I can take them in
this direction and I can't take them in that direction. That's the
case of the משנה. Mishna. But interesting to think about the scenario
I just mentioned. So הבהמה והכלים כרגלי הבעלים. Ha-behemah ve-ha-keilim k'raglei ha-baalim.
Goes like where the owner goes. המוסר בהמה לבנו או לרועה. Ha-moser
behemah livno o l'ro'eh. You give your animal to be shepherded to
your son or to a shepherd, and they have their עירוב eiruv
takes them in an opposite direction outside of your עירוב. eiruv. הרי
אלו כרגלי הבעלים. Harei elu k'raglei ha-baalim. It goes by you, it
goes by the owner, and they can't take your sheep outside of
what would be your עירוב. eiruv. כלים המיוחדים לאחד מן האחים שבבית.
Keilim ha-myuchadim l'echad min ha-achim she-ba-bayis.
Let's say there are brothers that have an estate that they have
not yet divided. Now some of the vessels maybe they have designated
is really for the use of one person. Even though we all
share the estate, you get to drive the pickup truck, I do
this, whatever it is. In that case, הרי אלו כרגליו, harei elu
k'raglav, even though maybe he doesn't own it in a legal sense
distinct from the other brothers, it's still part of the estate. Since
it's designated for him, it follows him.
ושאין מיוחדים, Ve-she-ein meyuchadim, and things that are equally shared, part of
the undifferentiated estate, הרי אלו כמקום שהלכו. harei elu k'makom she-halchu. Those
are limited. to the place where everybody can go, meaning it only
goes by the intersection of everybody's תחום. techum. So if I'll try
to describe this visually, I don't have a whiteboard, okay? But it's
let's say, right? Let's say, here, imagine that the city is in
the middle of these two, right? So therefore and this is 2,000
אמות amot in each direction. But I make my עירוב eiruv over
here. So therefore I can travel more in this direction, right? 'Cause
I'm sort of officially starting here, but less in that direction. You
make your עירוב eiruv over there. So you can travel so then
there could be a case where our well actually this would be
the most extreme case, okay? Where the עירובין eiruvin are completely don't
overlap. But there could be a case where there is some overlap,
right? I go 1,500 אמות amot up 3,500 אמות amot in one
direction and 500 in the other. You go 3,500 in that direction
and five anyway and then there could be you know a thousand
that's overlapped in the middle. So if we're sharing objects, the shared
objects can only go in that overlapped area between those two like
Venn diagrams,
between those two
you know עירובין eiruvin where
it could be no intersection.
Exactly, and we're going to get to that. Exactly. So it says
like this: השואל כלי מחבירו מערב יום טוב. hashoel kli mechavero me’erev
Yom Tov.
So if you borrow something again, this is underscoring the point that
it's not about ownership, it's more about under whose sort of control
and use it is. So if you borrow something on ערב יום
טוב, erev Yom Tov, so when יום טוב Yom Tov begins because
תחומין techumin are defined when יום טוב Yom Tov, begins, you know
בין השמשות. bein hashmashot. So then כרגלי השואל, keraglei hashoel, then it
goes by the borrower's because it was his what it was under
his control when יום טוב Yom Tov began. ביום טוב, beYom Tov,
if you borrowed it on יום טוב, Yom Tov, כרגלי המשאיל. keraglei
hamash’il. It goes by the lender because when יום טוב Yom Tov
began it was under the control of the lender, okay? So maybe
my example when I call you up before יום טוב Yom Tov
and I say can I use your you know can I use
your blankets or whatever? So maybe I'm already a שואל shoel because
we made even though I didn't that's another question also when do
I become a שואל? shoel? Only when I take possession of the
כלי? kli? Or when when you agree to let me use it?
We'll see some of that in the גמרא. Gemara
וכן האשה ששאלה מחבירתה תבלין ומים ומלח ועיסתה. vechen ha'ishah shesha'alah mechivertah
tavlin umayim umelach ve'issatah. A woman who's making dough and she's got
the flour but she had to borrow salt or water or spices.
So then this flour is dough is owned jointly is the you
know has both people's ownership. So הרי אלו כרגלי שתיהן, harei elu
keraglei sheteihen, then it goes like both of theirs, okay? Because it
has in it stuff that was defined by a different owner. So
even though when I lend it to you, I don't now cannot
say give me back my spices or in the dough, I don't
right now have an ownership of the dough, okay? You'll just have
to after יום טוב Yom Tov pay me back with other spices.
But nevertheless this dough contains something whose תחום, techum, even though I
lent it to you on יום טוב Yom Tov and it became
yours on יום טוב, Yom Tov but the תחום techum was already
defined when יום טוב Yom Tov? began and it's part of the
תחום techum here is pointing in the other direction. Alright? So again,
you understand the scenario. This woman borrows it so she takes possession
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. The dough is fully owned by her
but it contains spices that have a different תחום techum because when
יום טוב Yom Tov. began they were owned by somebody else. Alright?
So הרי אלו
כרגלי שתיהן. harei elu keraglei sheteihen. רבי יהודה פוטר במים מפני שאין
בהם ממש. Rabbi Yehudah poter bamayim mipnei she'ein bahem mamash. Rabbi Yehuda
says no, water is not included in being limited by תחום. techum.
Water is seen as insubstantial. Now really, water's insubstantial? I mean well
you do make a ברכה beracha on water. Water was like is
pretty much necessary for life. I mean so much of בראשית Bereishit
is about wells and water and so on. But the point is
is that you don't see its presence in the dough, okay? Spices
and salt you taste, maybe you even see if it's thick salt.
We'll talk about that. Water you do not see and you don't
sense its presence in the dough. So the dough is no longer
it loses the sense of that there's water in the dough and
therefore it becomes sort of invisible. Yes.
Could you just clarify something very basic? Like even today on שבת,
people can walk from here down to Manhattan, you know.
Yeah. Because when you draw the תחום techum around the city, you
take the outer limits, the outermost like inhabited places within the city
of continuous thing and then you make a rectangle around it based
on the four corners of the compass. The southernmost, you know, easternmost.
So
first of all that, and then once you do that, for example
for Manhattan or the Bronx, it'll wind up overlapping with Manhattan or
with New Jersey. And once that square overlaps with another city square,
they all become part of the same thing.
Because of geometry it goes way beyond 2,000 אמות. amot.
Not outside of the city. It's not how far you walk, it's
how far you walk outside of the city. Exactly. Okay, alright. גמרא.
Gemara מתניתין. Matnitin. Our משנה, mishna, דלא כרבי דוסא. dela keRabbi Dosa.
It's not like Rabbi Dosa. Turn the עמוד. amud. דרבי דוסא. deRabbi
Dosa. דתניא. detanya. We learned in a ברייתא. beraita. רבי דוסא אומר.
Rabbi Dosa omer. Rabbi Dosa says. ואמרי לה אבא שאול אומר. ve’amrei
lah Abba Shaul omer. Sometimes Abba Shaul. הלוקח בהמה מחבירו מערב יום
טוב. halokeach behemah mechavero me’erev Yom Tov.
You purchase an animal on ערב יום טוב. erev Yom Tov. אף
על פי שלא מסרה לו אלא ביום טוב הרי הוא כרגלי הלוקח.
af al pi shelo masrah lo ela beYom Tov harei hu keraglei
halokeach. And here's a similar example. When is it considered to be
under your control? Again, it's not about strict legal possession. So you
purchased it ערב יום טוב, erev Yom Tov, maybe you paid the
money, even though you didn't take possession of the animal, which by
the way is the technical act needed for legal ownership. Nevertheless, you're
already considered the owner and when for these purposes of תחום techum
and it follows your תחום, techum, you the purchaser's תחום techum because
you already had done the transaction on ערב יום טוב. Erev Yom
Tov. Again, it raises interesting questions for the case of borrowing. You
get permission to take something and borrow something ערב יום טוב, Erev
Yom Tov, you only take possession on יום טוב, Yom Tov based
on this, it could very well be that it's already considered under
your control because when יום טוב Yom Tov began you already had
the right to borrow. Here you've already done the actual purchase. So
that's point number one, you actually sort of transacted it even though
you haven't fully finalized it. Okay, and that's number one, we're not
going to focus on that. The next line: והמוסר בהמה לרועה, vehamoseir
beheima lero'eh, if you give over your animal to a shepherd, אף
על פי שלא מסרו לו אלא ביום טוב, af al pi shelo
masro lo ela biyom tov, even though you only gave it to
him on יום טוב, Yom Tov. הרי הוא כרגלי הרועה, harehu keraglei
haro'eh, it goes by the shepherd. So that's exactly against our משנה.
Mishnah. Our משנה Mishnah says that it goes by the owner, and
this says that it goes by the shepherd, even in the extreme
case where you gave it to him on יום טוב Yom Tov.
itself. So how so clearly our משנה Mishnah is not this ברייתא.
Beraita. גמרא Gemara says no, אפילו תימא רבי דוסא, afilu teima Rebbe
Dosa, our משנה Mishnah could be like רבי דוסא, Rebbe Dosa, ולא
קשיא, vlo kashya, it's not difficult, כאן ברועה אחד כאן בשני רועים.
kan bero'eh echad kan beshnei ro'im. A difference if there's only one
shepherd in the town or if there are two shepherds. Why should
it make a difference? Because if there's only one shepherd in the
town, then even if you haven't given it to the shepherd when
יום טוב Yom Tov. began, it's already assumed that you're going to
give it to, of course you'd give it to this shepherd, there's
only one shepherd. So therefore it's already assumed to be intended to
be given to him, so it's like it's already under his control.
So you see, on the one hand we say it goes by
the owner, on the other hand we're having a more and more
flexible definition of what the owner is. You don't, you haven't taken
possession of the thing you borrowed yet, that's what I said, you
haven't taken possession of the thing you bought yet, you're still considered
the owner. There's a desire, the case in the משנה, Mishnah, an
estate that hasn't been divided but something is fundamentally used by you.
And here we have a case where you haven't even given it
to a shepherd but it's assumed you'll give it to the shepherd
and that's already defined therefore by the shepherd.
Okay, if there's two shepherds and you don't know which one you'll
give it to, then it's not defined, you would have to give
it over on ערב יום טוב, Erev Yom Tov, giving it over
on יום טוב Yom Tov would not work. So the גמרא Gemara
says: דייקא נמי, deika nami, that's also can be implied from the
משנה, Mishnah, דתני לבנו או לרועה. detani livno o lero'eh. It gives
an example that there are two people you could give it to,
you give it either to your son or to the shepherd. So
if there's a choice to be made, then it's not defined when
יום טוב Yom Tov begins and then it would be defined by
your ownership. But if there's no choice to be made, then when
יום טוב Yom Tov begins it's already seen in the possession of
the shepherd. שמע מינה, shema mina, that is a good point.
גמרא Gemara is allowing us to assume who would receive it, but
the underlying issue really is when you had that thought, not to
whom?
No, no, no, because in the case of only one shepherd you
didn't need to have a thought. And in the case of two
shepherds, even if you had the thought and you had the plan,
since it wasn't sort of self-evident,
then the plan isn't enough. You'd have to have some actual giving
over or at least commitment to give it to him or maybe
at least some speech and so on. Okay, just thinking I was
planning on doing it, that would not be enough. Okay, if there's
only one shepherd it's like pre-defined it's going to him. Two shepherds,
you have to actually do it. Now again, what does it mean
to do it, to give it over before יום טוב? Yom Tov
How much of that is verbal, physical? We're already seeing some flexibility
with that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues: אמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבי דוסא, amar Rabbah bar bar
Chana amar Rebbe Yochanan halacha keRebbe Dosa, we go like רבי דוסא
Rebbe Dosa that it goes by the shepherd. So the גמרא Gemara
says: ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי, umi amar Rebbe Yochanan hachi, how
could רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan say that? האמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם
משנה, ha'amar Rebbe Yochanan halacha kestam Mishnah, we go like the סתם
משנה, stam Mishnah, ותנן, utenan, and our משנה Mishnah says it doesn't
go by the shepherd, הבהמה והכלים כרגלי הבעלים, habeheima vehakeilim keraglei habalim,
and it should have quoted the end of it, and it doesn't
go by the shepherd, especially certainly if you give it to the
shepherd on יום טוב. Yom Tov גמרא Gemara says what's the problem?
ולאו אוקימנא, velav okimnah, we already resolved it, כאן ברועה אחד כאן
בשני רועים. kan bero'eh echad kan beshnei ro'im. Our משנה Mishnah is
talking about two shepherds and רבי דוסא Rebbe Dosa is talking about
one. Of course then, so what רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan is saying
is when there's only one shepherd, we פסקן pasken like, like רבי
דוסא, Rebbe Dosa, that it's automatically defined by the shepherd. If there's
two shepherds or a shepherd and your son and there's a choice
to be made, then it would have to be given over on
ערב יום טוב. Erev Yom Tov. Okay, תנו רבנן, tano rabanan, we
taught: שנים ששאלו חלוק אחד בשותפות, shnayim shesha'alu chaluk echad beshutfus, two
people, and here we're going to get to your case though. Two
people borrowed a shirt or to use
in partnership. So they're equal borrowers of this shirt. זה לילבשו שחרית
לבית המדרש, zeh lilbesho shachris leveismidrash, one person wanted to use the
shirt to go to the בית המדרש beis hamidrash in the morning,
this is on יום טוב. Yom Tov וזה לילבשו ערבית לבית המשתה,
vezeh lilbesho arvit leveismishteh,
and the other one was going to use it on יום טוב
Yom Tov night, like מוצאי יום טוב, motzaei Yom Tov, but יום
טוב Yom Tov night, to go to a drinking party. Okay, two
very different people, you know, it's like יעקב Yaakov and עשו, Esav,
this one is running by בית המדרש, beis hamidrash, the other one
is running by, what does it say? ואף על גב דבית המשתה.
veaf al gav dbeismishteh.
Is it a wedding?
Yeah, it probably is a wedding, but it can't be a wedding
actually because it's יום טוב. Yom Tov Anyway, no, because if it's
מוצאי יום טוב, motzaei Yom Tov, רש״י Rashi explicitly says של יום
טוב, shel Yom Tov, ערבי של יום טוב. arvi shel Yom Tov.
It's מוצאי יום טוב, motzaei Yom Tov, it has no relevance for
the status on יום טוב. Yom Tov, They have to be in
partnership of it on יום טוב.
Yom Tov, Maybe he was from the other,
anyway, let's just move on. Fine, let's move on. זה עירב ולזו
*Zeh eirev u-le-zo*, they both want to use it on יום טוב
*Yom Tov* and they have divided up the day, night and day.
זה עירב ולזו צפון וזה עירב ולזו דרום *Zeh eirev u-le-zo tzafon
ve-zeh eirev u-le-zo darom*. One person put his עירוב *eiruv* in the
north so he can go 2,000 אמות *amot* to the north, or
4,000 אמות *amot* to the north, but he can't go any distance
to the south. The other one put his עירוב *eiruv* in the
south. He can go 4,000 אמות *amot* to the south, but he
can't even take one step to the north. So the actual intersection
is zero, right? You have that scenario? The intersection of their עירובים
*eiruvim* is zero, okay? So what's the הלכה *halacha*? They can sort
of meet, it's like the north-going Zax and the south-going, you ever
remember the Dr. Seuss? I can meet at the edge of my
עירוב *eiruv* and you can come up to the edge of yours
and we can maybe hand over the soup, but I can't step
into your zone and you can't step into my zone. Our zones
don't overlap. So what's the הלכה *halacha*? Now you might think, well
what's the problem? They're not using it for the same period of
time. Maybe one in the daytime, it's in the nighttime it's in
one zone and the daytime it's in another. No, you don't divide
יום טוב *Yom Tov* by half days. Its status has to be
defined for the whole day of יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So that's
what it says. זה שעירב ולזו צפון מהלך לצפון כרגלי מי שעירב
ולזו דרום *Zeh she-eirev u-le-zo tzafon mahalekh le-tzafon ke-raglei mi she-eirev u-le-zo
darom*. So the guy who made the northern one, he can take
it to the north only to the extent that the southern guy's
עירוב *eiruv* extends to the north. So I gave example it extended
zero, but maybe there is a thousand אמה *amah* overlap. So you
can take it to the north but only to the extent of
the southern guy's עירוב *eiruv*. וזה שעירב ולזו דרום *Ve-zeh she-eirev u-le-zo
darom*, the one who made who is going to the south, מהלך
לדרום כרגלי מי שעירב ולזו צפון *mahalekh le-darom ke-raglei mi she-eirev u-le-zo
tzafon*, only to the extent that the northern guy's עירוב *eiruv* goes
into the south. So it has to be the actual overlap of
their two zones. ואם מיצו את התחום *Ve-im mitzu et ha-tchum*, if
they divided the space, which basically means there's no overlap, this guy's
going all the way to the south and the other's all the
way to the north and there's absolutely no overlap. הרי זה לא
יזיזנו ממקומו *Harei zeh lo yezizenu mi-mkomo*, you can't move it, okay?
You cannot take the shirt anywhere. Okay, so you don't say, oh,
day and night, let's split it day and night. No, יום טוב
*Yom Tov*'s identity of תחומים tchumim. *tchumim* has to be for the
whole day, and there's no overlap and therefore it cannot be moved.
But can't you go to the edge and hand it over?
No, because then you're taking it from one תחום tchum *tchum* to
the next.
Right, so you can't stick your hand into the next zone.
Exactly. You can stick your hand, you can't transfer the object. Sure.
It's the shirt. The shirt's zone is, has you know, no shared
zone. איתמר *Itmar*. שנים שלקחו חבית ובהמה בשותפות *Shnayim she-lakhu chavit u-behema
be-shutafut*. Two people purchased a חבית *chavit* and a בהמה beheima? *behema*.
Now before we were talking about בהמה beheima. *behema* we were talking
about shepherds, but here the idea of בהמה beheima? *behema* is to
שחט shacht *shecht* it and eat it. Okay, so you had a
barrel of wine and you've got future steaks, okay? You got your
בהמה *behema* and you own it in partnership and you want to
divide it on יום טוב *Yom Tov* and you know you're going
to take half and I'm going to take half and we'll have
a very nice יום טוב *Yom Tov* meal. Okay, so but again,
we don't have necessarily overlapping תחומים *tchumim*, so what's going to be
the story? Is it going to be limited by our shared תחומים
*tchumim*? רב Rav אמר חבית מותרת *Rav amar chavit muteret*. The חבית
*chavit* you don't have to worry, that's not limited by your shared
תחומים *tchumim*. Each person takes it in their own תחום tchum *tchum*.
ובהמה אסורה *U-behema asura*, but the animal is forbidden, the animal is
limited by the overlap of the תחומים *tchumim*. ושמואל אמר חבית נמי
אסורה *Ve-Shmuel amar chavit nami asura*. That even the barrel is forbidden.
Now what's the logic here? So can you tell me what the
logic is by the barrel, why it should not be limited by
the overlap of the תחומים *tchumim*? We own a shared barrel on
יום טוב *Yom Tov*, we divide it up, I take half you
take half, and we can take each one can take their half
in their own תחום tchum *tchum*, they don't have to worry about
the overlap.
You said you can't tell which half was the, you could say
I got the front half, you got
the back half, and you could say that's... right. Well, yeah, but
the opposite, because the barrel, if you can't tell, then it should
be limited to both, right? So you have to say more, when
we divide the barrel, that shows it's a ברירה bereira. *bereira* case,
right? That shows that that half that I took of the wine
was always the half that was intended for me, so that was
never held בשותפות *be-shutafut*. The half I got was the half I
always owned, and therefore it's not בשותפות *be-shutafut* and your half is
the same. But by an animal, an animal is less, you know,
divisible. So therefore we might not be able to say ברירה bereira
*bereira*, this was always my half. Let's take a look at what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. So okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this: מאי קסבר רב
*Mai kasavar Rav*? What does רב *Rav* hold? אי קסבר יש ברירה
yesh bereira? *I kasavar yesh bereira* that retroactively we define once you
split it in half which half was yours, that half was always
yours. So אפילו בהמה תשתרי *afilu behema tishrei*, let's say the same
about the animal. Those steaks were always yours, the animal was alive
when יום טוב *Yom Tov* began, but now we שחט *shecht*ed it
and divided, and the other steaks were his, the other half of
the animal is his, and there was never a joint ownership, so
therefore you're not limited. ואי קסבר אין ברירה ein bereira. *Ve-i kasavar
ein bereira* and if you hold there's no ברירה bereira *bereira* that
when יום טוב *Yom Tov* began it was joint, it only got
separated on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, so אפילו חבית נמי אסורה *afilu
chavit nami asura* then it should be like שמואל *Shmuel*. שמואל *Shmuel*
says even the barrel of wine it's limited by the overlap, right?
It's forbidden, meaning it's limited by the overlap, because when יום טוב
*Yom Tov* began it was in partnership, whatever happened later happened later,
and therefore it's limited to the overlap of the two owners. So
how do you understand this difference between the barrel and the animal?
So the גמרא *Gemara* says: לעולם קסבר יש ברירה yeish bereira? *Le-olam
kasavar yesh bereira*. רב *Rav* holds there is ברירה bereira *bereira*. And
that works for... I get my wine on יום טוב, it turns
out that was the wine that was always mine and it's not
limited by the other person. So how about the animal?
ושאני בהמה, Veshani beheima, the animal is different, דקיימי תחומי מהדדי. dekaymi
tchumei mehadadi. The תחומין tchumin sort
of suck, they derive nutrients from one another. What does that mean?
So the way תוספות Tosafot explains it is the following. Good. Let's
say we will say ברירה.
And when יום טוב comes, let's make it easy. I wind up
taking, we שחט the animal, I wind up taking the front half
and you take the back half of the animal. So what was
the status? So we'll say retroactively that was always the story when
יום טוב began. יום טוב began, this animal, the front half was
mine and the back half was yours. So why are we limited
by one another? Because תוספות Tosafot says look, because the back half
is still deriving some of its sustenance from the front half and
the front half, I mean the blood is running throughout the animal,
it's deriving some of its sustenance from the back half. So even
if the front half was mine and the back half was yours,
my front half has in it something of yours, and your back
half has in it something of mine. So it's sort of like
the dough that has in it some other components and therefore it's
going to be limited by you. Each half will be limited by
the owner of the other half.
It's the same for the wine. Yeah, that's what I was going
to... No, the wine wasn't stuck together. How do you separate? It's
moving around.
It's moving around. But if we say that these droplets were the
droplets in the barrel that were always mine, we couldn't have identified
them, they never got anything when יום טוב began. If we could
have labeled the droplets that were mine and the droplets that were
yours, my droplets never got anything from your droplets.
Is that for the בהמה?
No, because even if a half is totally mine, while that half
is mine and while it's בין השמשות, bein hashmashot, it's getting nutrients
and blood and oxygen from your back half and the same is
true about your back half. So they're
actually organically and biologically dependent on one another. So therefore, even when
יום טוב begins and I retroactively see I had the front half,
it was a front half that had some things of yours in
it. Okay, so let's take a look. It's not because you can't
divide it. You can divide it, but it's still gaining from the
other half.
דקיימי תחומי מהדדי. Dekaymi tchumei mehadadi. אמרו ליה רב כהנא ורב אסי
לרב. Amru lei Rav Kahana veRav Assi leRav. So רב כהנא ורב
אסי Rav Kahana veRav Assi said to רב, I don't get it.
לאיסור מוקצה לא חשת ולאיסור תחומין חשת? Leissur muktzeh lo chasht veleissur
tchumin chasht?
This idea you have of ינקי מהדדי. yanki mehadadi. You're not going
to be concerned about מוקצה, muktzeh, but you are going to be
concerned about תחומין? tchumin? שתיק רב. Shtik Rav. And רב was silent.
So what concern about מוקצה muktzeh is it talking about? So תוספות
Tosafot says that he says like this. He says, if you're worried
about this invisible thing that's happening, that it's getting nutrients from the
back half, heck, let's say when יום טוב is beginning, let's say
it's a microscopic amount fatter today on יום טוב than it was
when יום טוב began. And that microscopic amount that it's fatter is
נולד nolad and is מוקצה muktzeh because it didn't have that extra
gram of meat on its bones. So obviously we're not going to
look at things with a microscope to say that extra gram of
meat that grew between יום טוב night and today is מוקצה muktzeh
and נולד. nolad. So also we're not going to look at this
blood thing to say that it's a תחומין tchumin problem. Okay? That's
the analogy. I don't know if it's such a persuasive analogy.
Anyway, he says the word תחומין tchumin in ינקי תחומי yanki tchumei
means not the תחומין tchumin we've been talking about, it means the
sections of the בהמה.
No, no, no, but the section your animal has its תחום tchum.
and my animal half has its תחום tchum and the thing that
has one תחום tchum is deriving nutrients from the thing that has
the defined by the other תחום. tchum. You mean the area of
the בהמה? No, no, תחום tchum. meaning labeled for ראובן's Reuven תחום
and labeled for שמעון's Shimon תחום. Okay. All right. Sorry. I'm sorry.
Okay, so the גמרא says like this. Okay. So שתיק רב. Shtik
Rav. He didn't have an answer to that מוקצה muktzeh analogy. Now
the גמרא says מאי הוי עלה? Mai havya ala? What was the
upshot? רב אושעיא אמר יש ברירה. Rav Oshaya amar yesh bereira. There
is ברירה and both the wine is okay and the animal's okay.
If you wind up splitting it on יום טוב, you can't split
the day. This is in contrast to the shirt. Day and night
is still the same undivided shirt. But when you divide the animal
and the wine, retroactively that was always your half and it's not
limited by the other person's תחום. רבי יוחנן אמר אין ברירה. Rabbi
Yochanan amar ein bereira. There isn't ברירה and both the wine and
the animal are אסור and they're not defined and they are limited
to the overlapping of the two תחומין. tchumin. So the גמרא says
וסבר רב אושעיא יש ברירה? Vesavar Rav Oshaya yesh bereira? Does רב
אושעיא Rav Oshaya really hold יש ברירה? yeish bereira. והתנן, Vehatnan, we
taught in a משנה: Mishnah: המת בבית ולו פתחים הרבה. Hamet babayit
velo ptachim harbe. Now we had this whole thing earlier so I'll
do this pretty quickly although it's very late. המת בבית ולו פתחים
הרבה. Hamet babayit velo ptachim harbe. There's a corpse in the house
and the house has many openings. And the, so any exit you'll
take the corpse out of is considered like the טומאה tumah is
already going through that exit. And if you can't identify which is
the exit, it's like all of them are potential exits and the
טומאה tumah goes through all of them. כולם טמאים. Kulam tmeim. נפתח
אחד מהם. Niftach echad mehem. If one of the doors are open
and that's going to be the door that are now by almost
by definition because it's open that you'll assume to take the מת
meis out of, הוא טמא, hu tamei, that doorway is טמא, tamei,
וכולם טהורים, vechulam tehorim, the others are טהור tahor because they're not
the future exits of the מת. meis. חשב להוציאו באחד מהם, chishev
le'hotzio be'echad meihem, let's say you just intend, you don't actually do
an act, you intend to take it out of one door, או
בחלון, o be'chalon, or even a window, שיש בו ארבעה על ארבעה,
she'yesh bo arba'a al arba'a, four טפחים tefachim by four טפחים, tefachim,
which is the minimum to be considered an exit for the מת.
meis. So just planning on doing it defines it as the exit,
ומציל על כל הפתחים כולם, umatzil al kol ha'p'tachim kulam, that saves
the other doorways from being טמא, tamei, that's like opening the door,
that defines that as the exit, just thinking about it. בית שמאי
אומר, Beis Shammai omer, והוא שחשב עליו עד שלא ימות המת. vehu
she'chishev alav ad she'lo yamus ha'meis. No, that idea that thinking can
define it as the exit is only if it was identified as
such before the person died. But once the person died and all
the exits were potential exits, thinking does not redefine one over the
other. ובית הלל אומר, uve'veit Hillel omer, אף משימות המת, af mishe'yamus
ha'meis, even after the person dies, that identifying with your mind, even
without doing anything, of one exit, defines that as the exit and
not the other thing. All that is very interesting. The question is,
once you now have one thing defined as the exit and that's
טמא tamei and the other doors are טהור, tahor, does that definition
work retroactively? Right, you understand the scenario. You've got a house, there's
a dead body in it, there are vessels under the threshold of
the various exits. Once,
initially, all the exits are טמא. tamei. You open up the door,
that one is טמא, tamei, the others are טהור. tahor. So that
certainly works going forward. What about the things that were in the
thresholds of the other exits before I opened up the door? Will
it work retroactively or not? And that's a ברירה question. Once one
is defined as the exit, do I now look back and say
that one was always going to be the exit? Okay.
Was this either whether before you did this before the person died
or after the person died?
No, we're not, no,
let's not. No, it means you opened it after the person died.
After the person died, what's the story retroactively if there are things
that were in the threshold? So we'll just read the one answer,
I know we're a little bit over, but ואיתמר עלה, ve'itmar alah,
אמר רבי אושעיא, amar Rabbi Oshaya, לטהר הפתחים מכאן ולהבא, le'taher ha'p'tachim
mikan u'leha'ba,
that this debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis
Shammai or the whole discussion here is going
forward, מכאן ולהבא mikan u'leha'ba in, only
going forward, למפרע
לא, l'mafrea lo, but even after you've defined an exit, that does
not retroactively say that things that were in the thresholds before are
טהור, tahor, it doesn't retroactively define it as the exit. So the
whole point of this is showing that רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya holds
אין ברירה. ein bereira, What you do doesn't retroactively define. And the
question is why does here he hold אין ברירה, ein bereira but
when it comes to the wine and the animal he seems to
hold יש ברירה? If you split it on יום טוב, then it's
not limited by the overlapping of the תחומים. Okay? So we will
leave ourselves with that question. We will figure out how to reconcile
it, but at least we see on the face of it, רבי
אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya here holds אין ברירה by the מת meis and
the door, and by the case of the wine and the animal
he seems to hold יש ברירה. חזק חזק. chazak chazak.